Two episodes ago we did our first format string exploit and in the last video we had a look
两集前，我们第一次使用了格式字符串漏洞，而在上集视频中，
at how dynamically linking libraries to a binary works - basically how can a program
我们看了一下，关于如何将库动态链接到二进制文件，
call functions from libc.
基本上来说就是，程序是如何从 libc 调用函数的。
And we also had an idea how to abuse this, when we want to redirect code execution.
当我们想要重定向代码执行时，我们还要有利用它的想法。
In this video we will use this technique to exploit format level 4 from exploit exercises
在本视频中，我们将使用此技术，利用格式级别4，
protostar.
还是来自 exploit exercises protostar 的练习。
First let’s have a look at the code.
首先，让我们看看代码。
The main function calls vuln.
main 函数调用 vuln。
Vuln reads up to 512 characters from standard input into the buffer.
vuln 从标准输入，读取最多512个字符到缓冲区。
And then uses printf to print the buffer.
然后，使用 printf 打印缓冲区。
We also see immediatly that the buffer is places as the first parameter of printf - and
我们还立即看到缓冲区，是 printf 的第一个参数。
that is the format parameter.
而这个是格式参数。
After the printf there is a call to exit().
在 printf 之后，将调用exit() 。
This means that this function vuln will never return.
这意味着这个函数，vuln 永远不会返回。
It will perform the syscall exit to the kernel, which will quit this process.
它将执行内核的 syscall 退出函数，退出此进程。
So if we would overwrite the return pointer of this function, we would never return and
所以，即便我们覆盖这个函数的返回指针，我们还是永远不会返回
we could not exploit it.
，也就不能利用它。
So we use the technique from the last video to overwrite the GOT entry for exit, with
因此，我们使用上一个视频中的技术，覆盖 GOT 的 exit 条目，
the address for hello.
换成 hello 的地址。
That instead of exit we execute hello at the end.
这样就不是退出，而是在最后执行 hello。
Let’s get everything ready.
让我们把一切准备好。
I use again vmware to run the protostar image and connect to it via ssh with putty.
我再次使用vmware，运行ProtoStar映像，并使用 putty ，通过 ssh连接到它。
Open one window for the binary.
打开一个窗口，给予二进制文件。
And another window where we can write the exploit.
以及另一个我们可以编写漏洞的窗口。
We also might want to import the struct module right away, because we need that to convert
我们也可能希望立即导入 struct 模块，
integers to binary strings.
因为我们需要它，把整数转换成二进制字符串。
Let’s start by first verifying that we have a format string vulnerability.
让我们首先验证一下，是否存在格式字符串漏洞。
We can just specify some format characters and see if they are turned into numbers.
我们可以指定一些格式字符，看看它们是否转换成数字。
Yup!
是的！
That works.
有效。
So to make this exploit work we have to figure out a few addresses.
所以要想利用这个漏洞，我们必须找出一些地址。
Let’s get the address of the hello function with “x” examine hello.
让我们用“x”检查 hello，来获取 hello 函数的地址。
Here it is.
就是它。
Let’s copy that into our exploit script.
让我们把它，复制到我们的漏洞脚本中。
You can do that easily by simply highlighting the area you want to copy and then perform
只需高亮要复制的区域，
a mouse right click in the other window.
然后执行在另一个窗口中，单击鼠标右键就好。
Next let’s try to find the global offset table where we want to write this HELLO address
接下来，让我们试着找到全局偏移量表，我们要在其中，写入这个 hello 地址。
to.
去。
Disassemble main.
反汇编 main。
Ok.
好啊。
Right.
对了。
I forgot.
我忘了。
We call vuln.
我们，调用了 vule。
So disassemble vuln.
所以反汇编 vuln。
And at the bottom you can see the call to exit at the procedure linkage table ptl.
在底部，您可以看到在过程链接表 ptl 的退出调用。
Disassemble that address and we can now see the address that is referenced in this first
反汇编那个地址，我们现在可以看到，
instruction with the jump.
第一个带跳转的指令，所引用的地址。
That tries to reference the address of exit from glibc from there.
它试图引用来自 glibc ，退出的地址。
So examine that address.
所以，检查一下那个地址。
And yup.
和 yup 瞧。
That’s the global offset table.
这是全局偏移表。
Now we also store that table address in our script.
现在，我们还将该表地址，存储在脚本中。
Now let’s set two breakpoints in vuln.
现在，让我们在 vuln 中，设置两个断点。
One before the printf.
一个在 printf 前面。
And one after the printf.
一个在 printf 后面。
Next let’s simulate by hand overwriting the got entry.
接下来，让我们手动模拟，覆盖 GOT 条目 。
So we run the code.
让，我们运行代码。
At the printf we then change the entry of exit in the global offset table to hello and
在 printf 中，我们将 GOT 中的exit条目，更改为 hello ，
continue to execute the exit at the end of vuln.
并继续执行到 vuln 末尾 的 exit。
Run. we enter some random input.
run。我们键入，一些随机输入。
First breakpoint.
第一个断点。
Now we are befoire the printf.
现在，我们在 printf 之前。
Now let’s overwrite the GOT entry.
现在，让我们覆盖GOT条目。
Let’s check GOTagain.
我们，再检查一下Got。
Now write set, in curly braces int, the address we want to write to and then the value we
现在写入设定，大括号 int ，写入想写的地址，然后
want to write.
写入想写的值。
And now the entry for exit in the got has changed.
现在GOT的 exit 条目已经改变了。
Continue once.
继续来一次。
Now we are after the porintf.
现在，我们在找 printf。
Just one instruction away from the call to exit.
只有一条指令，可以从 该 call，到 eixt。
Next instruction.
下一条指令。
And disassemble and info registers.
以及反汇编和 info 寄存器。
Yup, we are at the exit.
是的，我们在 exit 处。
So let’s continue and see if we execute exit, or hello.
那么让，我们看看，继续执行的是 exit，还是hello。
Whoop.
呼呼。
Ok. we executed hello.
好呀。我们执行了 hello 。
That worked.
效果不错。
Now we just have to achieve this write with a format string and percentage n.
现在，我们只需要用一个格式字符串和 "%n" ，来实现这一写操作。
Ok.
好啊。
Step one.
第一步。
Let’s exit the debugger and let’s find the string we enter on the stack by playing
让我们退出调试器，通过在格式说明符周围找到，
around with the format specifiers.
我输入到栈中的字符串。
We use our script to do those tests.
我们使用脚本进行，这些测试。
So first we know the buffer is 512 bytes long.
但是首先，我们要知道缓冲区是512字节长。
So let’s write a function that pads our string to that length.
所以，让我们编写一个函数，将字符串填充到这个长度。
So we simply append a certain number of characters to our string, where that number is 512 minus
基本来说，我们只需在字符串中，附加一定数量的字符，其中该数目为
the length of the current string.
512 减去 当前字符串的长度。
Then we create a variable exploit and print that variable padded.
然后，我们创建一个变量漏洞，并打印该填充的变量。
And when we execute it we can see our exploit string and that it’s padded to those 512
当我们执行它时，我们可以看到我们的漏洞字符串，
characters.
它被填充到512字符。
So this will print the first 4 values from the stack.
所以，这将打印栈中的前4个值。
Yup seems to work.
是的，似乎有用。
Now let’s prepend some recognizable characters to the string and then try to see how far
现在，让我们在字符串前面，加上一些可识别的字符，然后试着看看，
away our string is on the stack.
我们的字符串在那栈上有多远。
Ha!
哈！
Cool.
酷。
Ok.
好啊。
Our string already starts with the 4th value.
我们的字符串，已经以第4个值开始。
Now we can use the number dollar notation in the format string to specifically reference
现在，我们可以使用格式字符串中的数字美元符号，
that offset.
来具体指定便宜。
So 4 dollar after the percentage sign.
所以，在百分比符号之后是 4 美元。
That would attempt to reference the 4th parameter of printf instead of going through the parameters
这将尝试引用 printf 的第4个参数，
one after another.
而不是一个接一个地遍历这些参数。
See, now all values are 41414141.
现在，所有值都是 41414141。
I hope you remember that percentage n can be used to write the number of printed characters
我希望你记得 "%n" ，
to an address on the stack.
能写出打印字符的栈地址。
So we could replace our a characters with the address of the global offset table address
所以，我们可以用我们的一个字符，替换全局偏移表地址，
to write to that value.
用来写入该值。
Let’s try it.
让我们试试看。
We use struct to convert the integer address to a binary string.
我们使用 struct 将整数地址，转换为二进制字符串。
Struct.
Struct。
Pack.
Pack。
I. exit_plt.
一、exit_plt。
Yup, we seem to hit that address.
是的，我们好像找到了那个地址。
Let’s replace the percentage x with percentage n and see what that does in gdb.
让我们将 "%x"替换为 "%n" ，看看在gdb中，它有什么作用。
But first write the output of this script to a file so we can use it in gdb as input.
但首先将这个脚本的输出，写入一个文件，这样我们就可以在gdb中，使用它作为输入。
Don’t forget to set the breakpoints again.
不要忘记，再次设置断点。
Run and pipe in the exploit string.
在漏洞字符串中，运行和管道。
And we hit the breakpoint.
我们到达了断点。
So now we are about to execute the printf.
所以，现在我们要执行 printf。
Let’s check the GOT entry.
让我们检查一下GOT条目。
Now let’s execute the printf and let’s check again.
现在让我们执行 printf，并再次检查。
HA!
哈！
We have overwritten GOT. with a fairly small number.
我们已经覆盖了GOT。是一个很少的数。
If we now continue we will segfault in exit, because at this address is no function.
如果我们现在继续，我们将在 exit 会有分段错误，因为在这个地址是没有函数的。
So percentage n has sucessfully written the number of characters printed into the GOT
因此， "%n" 把打印字符数，成功写入
table.
GOT表。
Now all we gotta do is print enpugh characters so that we reach the number that is the address
现在我们所要做的就是，把足够数量的字符打印出来，
of hello.
这样我们就能到达 hello 地址。
Mhmh… hex 0x80484b4.
MHMH… hex 0x80484B4。
Damn… that’s a big number.
该死的… 这是个大数字。
We have to print like over 134 MILLIOPn characters.
我们必须打印超过134百万个字符。
Each character is a byte so we have to print like 128 megabyte of text?
每个字符都是一个字节，所以我们必须像128兆字节，一样打印文本？
Will that work?
这样行吗？
Well, first of all we only have space for 512 characters in the buffer.
首先，缓冲区中，只有512个字符的空间。
So we can’t simply write them all.
所以，我们不能简单地把它们都写下来。
But we can abuse printf format strings again to pad an output string to any size.
但我们可以再次滥用printf格式字符串，将输出字符串，填充到任何大小。
Which allows us to write way more characters.
这样，我们可以写更多的字符。
Let’s try that.
我们试试看。
Let’s also change the number of ns down to only one.
我们也将 n 的数目,改为只有一个。
Ah. infact let’s change it back to x, so we don’t smash the table all the time and
啊。事实上，我们把它改回 x，这样我们就不会，一直轰炸表格了。
we can make sure we always hit the address.
我们可以确保，始终触碰到地址。
So let’s pad this to to like 30 characters, to see if that works.
所以，让我们把这个字符垫高，比如说30个字符，看看是否有效。
Oh and we must not forget to add another %x afterwards, which we will later replace with
哦，我们不能忘了，在后面再加一个 %x，
percentage n.
稍后我们会替换成"%n"
Run it against the format4 binary.
对 format4 二进制文件运行它。
And yes.
当然还有。
See all those spaces.
查看所有这些空间。
Text got padded to 30 characters.
文本被填充到30个字符。
Now le’ts try that with 134 million.
现在，我们要用1.34亿，来试试。
Okay. seems to work.
可以。似乎起作用了。
It’s printing and printing and printing.
它是在一直打印，打印，打印。
All those millions of spaces.
这可是，以亿计的所有空间。
This taks aaaages.
花上一个世纪的时间的感觉。
And we arrived at the end.
我们到达了终点。
Let’s try that in gdb again with percentage n.
让我们用 "%n" 在gdb中，再试一次。
Urgh man.
呃，伙计。
This takes so long…
这需要很长时间…
:( Printing those hundret megabytes is just crazy.
:( 打印那些百兆字节，简直是疯了。
But it did change the global offset table pretty close to hello.
但它确实改变了全球偏移表，非常接近hello。
We just would have to fiddle around a bit and adjust it exactly.
我们只需要，稍作调整就行了。
But you know what?
但你知道吗？
This sucks to print so many characters.
印这么多字，真是太糟了。
Let’s use a little trick.
让我们用点小技巧。
Let’s use TWO shorter writes to achieve the same.
让我们使用两个较短的写入，来实现相同的结果。
The idea is that we could first write the lower two bytes with a much smaller value,
这个想法是，我们可以先用一个小得多的值，写下低位的两个字节，
and then perform another write at address +2 to write another small value to the higher
然后在 地址+2 处执行另一个写入操作，将另一个较小的值，写入高位字节
bytes.
字节。
Thus constructing the whole 4 byte through two writes.
因此，通过两次写入，构造整个4字节。
So let’s try to write the lower two bytes first.
所以，让我们先写下低位的两个字节。
Let’s start with a padding like 30.
让我们从30这样的填充数开始。
Write the output again into the file.
再次将输出写入文件。
And run gdb with it as input.
并以它作为输入，运行gdb。
Ok, so with the padding of 30 we were able to write hex 2e, which is 46.
好的，填充30，我们就可以写 hex 2e，也就是 46。
Our goal is to write the two lower bytes so we want 84b4, which is 33972.
我们的目标是写下，两个低位的字节，所以，我们需要 84B4，即33972。
Because we had a padding of 30, but we ended up at 46 we have to compensate for those 16
因为，我们有30个填充物，但最终我们是 46 结尾的，我们必须推掉，
characters.
16个字符填充物。
So we substract 16 from it, so we want to put 33960 as a padding.
所以，我们从中减去16，我们想把 33960 作为填充。
And when we run it and look at the GOT entry, we can confirm that the two lower bytes are
当我们运行它，并查看GOT条目时，我们可以确认，
now 84b4.
低位两字节现在是84B4。
Now to address the two higher bytes we move our address by two forward.
现在，要处理两个高位的字节，我们将地址向前移动两个字节。
And perform another write.
再写一次。
So let’s add this address as well.
所以，我们也添加这个地址。
So EXIT_PLT plus 2.
所以 EXIT_PLT 加2。
This means that for the second write we want to address the fith element on the stack.
这意味着，对于第二次写入，我们要处理栈上的第三元素。
And now we just have to figure out how many we need to write here.
现在，我们只需要弄清楚我们需要在这里写多少。
Let’s try with 30 again.
我们再试试 30。
Ok.
好啊。
The lower two bytes now stay 84b4.
低位两字节，现在保持84b4。
Perfect.
很完美。
And the higher bytes are 84d2.
更高的字节是 84d2。
But we want to get 0804.
但我们想得到 0804。
So how do we get a lower number if we can only increase the amount of characters?
那么，如果我们只能增加字符的数量，我们如何才能得到一个更低的数字呢？
Well, in reality we don’t only write two bytes, we always write 4 bytes, this means
实际上，我们不只是写两个字节，我们总写四个字节，
that also currently we screw up data that is stored behind our exit GOT entry.
这意味着目前，我们也会把存储在 eixt 条目后面的数据刮下来。
Now guess what happens if we write enough to increase the number such that the 3rd byte
现在猜猜，如果我们写的足够多让值递增，
is 1 and the rest becomes 0 again.
以至于第3个字节为1，其余值再次变为0。
It doesn’t matter for the GOT, because it will only see the other 4 bytes.
对于GOT来说，这并不重要，因为它只会看到其他4个字节。
So basically we overflow those two upper bytes so we can get there a lower value in.
所以基本上，我们溢出这两个高位字节，这样较低的值就上来了。
Now currently we have 84d2.
现在，我们有84d2。
And we want 0804.
我们要0804。
I mean.
我意思。
We actually want 10804.
实际上，想要的是 10804。
And if we substract now the 84d2 from this we know how much we should write the get to
如果，我们现在把84d2从这里减去，
10804.
我们知道我们应该写多少，才能得到 10804。
So 8332.
就是 8332。
But that’s hex, so that is 33586.
但这个十六进制的，换算下就是33586。
And it already included the 30 padding.
它已经包括了，30个填充物。
So we must not forget that.
所以，我们不能忘记这一点。
Now we might be done.
现在，我们可能完成了。
Let’s check.
让我们检查一下。
We write the output file.
我们编写输出文件。
We run gdb.
我们运行GDB。
We break before the printf.
我们在 printf 之前，就断点下了。
This is how the table entry looks before.
这就是表格条目，以前的样子。
Now continue and examine the address again.
现在继续，并再次检查地址。
Wh00p.
哇。
We changed it.
我们改变了它。
And that’s the address of hello.
这是 hello 的地址。
So now continue and let the program run.
现在，继续运行程序。
BOOM. code execution redirected.
掌声。代码执行已重定向。
We win!
我们赢了！
It’s crazy how a harmless looking function like printf can be used to control the instruction
像 printf 这样看起来无害的函数，
pointer.x
如何被用来控制指令 pointer.x ，真是太雕了